<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sunetrike.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://sunetrike.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-24T00:24:34+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">sunE</title><subtitle>Wake up to the world that solar and Low Speed Electric Vehicles (LSEVs) can offer the Philippines</subtitle><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><entry><title type="html">In flight, I attain a higher consciousness. Fear disappears - Translation of Bertrand Piccard’s interview on La Croix</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/in-flight-i-attain-a-higher-consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In flight, I attain a higher consciousness. Fear disappears - Translation of Bertrand Piccard’s interview on La Croix" /><published>2021-09-23T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-09-23T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/in-flight-i-attain-a-higher-consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/in-flight-i-attain-a-higher-consciousness/">&lt;p&gt;Last month, Capt Piccard sat down with the Malo Tresca and the podcast &lt;em&gt;Place des Religions&lt;/em&gt; for a discussion about exploration, consciousness and how the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/efficient-solutions&quot;&gt;Solar Impulse Network of 1000 Solutions&lt;/a&gt; can contribute to the great existential challenge of the 21st century.  I decided to do a translation into English.  I opted to do this for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just for fun and French practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To reflect more on where Solar Impulse might be heading with its newest initiative and tagline &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/beyond-1000-solutions&quot;&gt;Ecology as driving force for economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I really want to see this initiative succeed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merci à &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lmgconsultancy.com/&quot;&gt;LMG Consultancy&lt;/a&gt; for double-checking my work! I was reminded that I still have a long road ahead of me on my journey to francophony  :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.la-croix.com/Religion/PODCAST-Bertrand-Piccard-En-vol-jatteins-degre-conscience-peur-disparait-2021-04-14-1201150811&quot;&gt;Here is the link to the podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;00:29 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D’habitude, tout le monde me parle de mon père et de mon grand-père, qui sont des explorateurs qui ont apporté énormément au 20ème siècle, mais c’est vrai qu’avoir une mère qui vous prend au sérieux comme enfant dans votre recherche de compréhension de la vie, de la mort, de Dieu et des autres, c’est extraordinaire.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Usually everyone talks to me about my father and grandfather, who were explorers that contributed enormously to the 20th century. But it’s really my mother takes you seriously as a child in searching to understand life, death, God and others. It’s extraordinary.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;00:33 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;L’aéronaute suisse, Bertrand Piccard, a réalisé, avec ses coéquipiers, deux tours du monde inédits. L’un à bord d’un ballon, poussé par les vents et l’autre aux commandes de l’avion Solar Impulse, alimenté grâce à l’énergie solaire.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviator Bertrand Piccard, together with his team, accomplished two 2 unprecedented trips around the wind: in a balloon pushed along by the winds.  On board the airplane Solar Impulse, fed graciously by solar energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;00:46 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pour lui, ces expériences ont été des défis techniques, mais aussi de grands voyages intérieurs. Bertrand Piccard se consacre désormais à un nouveau projet, celui de réunir 1000 solutions rentables pour protéger l’environnement, qu’il compte ensuite soumettre aux grandes instances décisionnaires mondiales. Une idée qu’il a expliqué au pape François, lors d’une entrevue au Vatican en février 2020.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For him, These experiences were technical challenges but also great voyages inwards.  Bertrand Piccard has now established a new project. This time to assemble a roster of 1000 profitable solutions for protecting the environment. He plans to submit them to the world’s great decision making bodies.  An idea which he explained to Pope Francis at the Vatican last February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01:12 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Je m’appelle Malo Tresca, je suis journaliste à La Croix et j’ai rencontré Bertrand Piccard à Lausanne. Dans ce podcast, des personnalités qui ont fait l’expérience du danger, nous confient leurs grands questionnements spirituels. Vous écoutez la troisième saison de « place des religions ».&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am Malo Tresca, I’m a journalist at La Croix and I’m meeting Bertrand Piccard in Lausanne. In this podcast, are the people who have experienced the face of danger and discuss with us their great spiritual questions. You are listening to the third season de place des Religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01:35 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bonjour Bertrand Piccard.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Bertrand Piccard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01:36 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bonjour&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01:42 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous nous faites aujourd’hui voyager à Lausanne, au siège de la Fondation Solar Impulse, dont vous êtes l’initiateur et le président. Le thème de l’aviation est partout dans la pièce où nous nous trouvons, dans ses tableaux, dans ses sculptures. Est-ce que vous pourriez nous redire un peu ce que représente pour vous aujourd’hui ce lieu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are joining you today in Lausanne, at the HQ of the Solar Impulse Fondation, of which you are founder and president. The aviation theme is everywhere in this room, On the tables and sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01:54 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Est ce que vous pourriez nous redire un peu ce que représente pour vous aujourd’hui ce lieu?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you tell us a bit about what this place represents for you today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01:58 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;C’est le lieu où je reçois les membres de mon équipe, les journalistes, les invités, simplement ma salle de réunion, de rencontre. Il y a forcément l’histoire de l’aviation parce que j’ai une certaine nostalgie de cette histoire incroyable où des pionniers ont ouvert la voie au risque de leur vie. Et puis, il y a quand même l’autre partie qui est celle de la spiritualité orientale, avec des objets tibétains, birmans, thaïlandais qui sont plus du monde intérieur que du monde extérieur de l’aviation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the place where I meet with my team, journalists and guests, simply my meeting room. I had to incorporate the history of aviation because I have a certain nostalgia about this incredible story where these pioneers have paved the way while risking their lives. Also, there is the other part which is the Oriental Spirituality, with Tibetan, Burmese, Thai objects which are more about the internal world than the exterior world of aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;02:23 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Passionné d’exploration depuis l’enfance, vous aviez de qui tenir avec vos aïeux. Vous êtes devenu l’un des pionniers du vol libre en delta-plane et de l’UL dans les années 1970. Qu’est ce qui vous attirait particulièrement dans cette voie des airs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion for exploration since childhood, which you had to keep up with your ancestors. You’ve become the first of the pioneers to fly delta-wing and UL (gliders) in the 1970s. What is it that attracted you to this type of flying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;02:35 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;J’ai eu des « role models », des inspirateurs dans le monde de l’aviation. Des astronautes, Charles Lindberg, tous ces pionniers que j’ai eu la chance de rencontrer quand j’étais enfant. J’habitais aux Etats-unis, j’ai assisté à six décollages d’Apollo, rencontré presque tous les astronautes de la NASA et des pionniers de l’histoire de l’aviation et je les rencontrais après avoir lu dans des livres toutes leurs histoires. Et ça a, pour moi, abolit toute frontière entre le rêve et la réalité. Je rêvais de ça et je les rencontrais.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had several role models in the world of aviation. The astronauts, Charles Lindberg, all the pioneers that I got the opportunity to meet when I was a child. I was living in the United States. I helped out on six Apollo launches and met all the NASA astronauts and other pioneers of the history of aviation and then also came across them in the books about all of their stories. So that, for me, demolished all boundaries between dream and reality. I was dreaming about it and I met them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;03:10 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Je voyais qu’ils réalisaient l’impossible. Et pour moi, ça a été une immense source d’inspiration. Je me suis dit que j’aimerais être explorateur. J’aimerais aller me confronter à l’inconnu, faire des choses que personne n’a jamais faites. Et j’ai acquis une certaine boussole dans mon cœur qui montrait non pas le Nord, mais qui montrait l’inconnu, tout ce qui n’avait encore jamais été fait. Et quand j’avais 16 ans, j’ai vu voler une des premières ailes Delta qui étaient apparues en Europe et je me suis dit, bien ça, c’est nouveau, ça c’est pour moi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had seen them realize the impossible. For me, that’s a huge source of inspiration. I told myself that I would like to be an explorer. I would like to go confront the unknown, do the things that no one has ever done. I’ve developed a certain compass in my heart that directs me, not to the North, but to the unknown, everything which has not already been done. Then when I was 16 years old, I saw the flight of one of the first hang-gliders that appeared in Europe and I told myself ‘Ah, this is new, this is for me’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;03:28 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ça c’est de nouveau quelque chose à explorer qui n’a pas encore été fait. Et c’est comme ça que j’ai commencé à voler. A 16 ans, je volais sous un triangle de toile, quelques tubes d’aluminium, à plusieurs milliers de mètres d’altitude. Et ce qui était fascinant là dedans, ce n’était pas simplement le fait de découvrir le vol, c’était de se découvrir soi-même. J’étais plutôt timoré à l’époque, je voulais être explorateur, mais en même temps, j’avais peur de monter dans un arbre.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the new thing to explore which hasn’t already been done. So just like that I started to fly. At 16 years old, I flew under a triangle of canvass, some tubes of aluminum, at several thousand metres altitude. And what was fascinating, was not just the act of learning to fly, it was also about discovering yourself. I was rather fearful at the time. I wanted to be an explorer, but at the same time, I was scared to climb a tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;04:05 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Puis, tout à coup, je me retrouvais en aile delta, confronté à moi-même, avec la responsabilité de ma vie entre les mains. Et ça, c’est des moments qui développent une conscience de soi qui est extraordinaire. Et quand on est en relation avec soi-même, quand on se sent vivre à l’intérieur de son corps, on développe une performance insoupçonnée. Et tout à coup, je me suis dit que je suis capable de faire beaucoup, beaucoup plus de choses que ce que je pensais.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then suddenly, I found myself in a hang-glider, confronting myself, with the responsibility for my life in my hands. It’s these moments that develop a self consciousness that is extraordinary. And when one is in touch with their own self, when one feels alive to the core of their body, one develops unexpected performance. And suddenly, I tell myself I am capable of doing a lot.  A lot more things than I can imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;04:30 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et l’aile delta, pour moi, c’était vraiment de l’initiation au monde de l’exploration, de l’aventure, mais aussi de la spiritualité, parce que je parlais beaucoup de spiritualité avec ma mère. C’était quelque chose de très théorique, puis tout à coup, je voyais à quel point on pouvait avoir ces flashs de conscience, à quel point on pouvait être en parfaite possession de toutes ces ressources dans l’instant présent. Et ça, c’était une révélation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the hang glider, For me, it’s really the entry into the world, of exploration, of adventure, but also of spirituality. Because I was talking often about spirituality with my mother. It was something very theoretical and suddenly, I was flying and I saw how we can get these flashes of consciousness. How much we can be in perfect possession of all these resources in the present instant. And that, it was a revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;04:53 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous avez fait beaucoup de chemin depuis, en 1999, après deux échecs, vous avez bouclé le premier tour du monde en ballon sans escale avec l’Anglais Brian Jones. 19 jours et 21 heures de vol, une odyssée qui a été considérée comme la dernière grande aventure du 20ème  siècle. Qu’est-ce qui vous a vraiment porté à croire, envers et contre tout, que vous pouviez aller au bout de ce rêve impossible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve come a long way since 1999 after two failures. You have accomplished the first non-stop round the world flight in a balloon with Englishman Brian Jones. 19 jours and 21 hours, an odyssey which was considered the last great adventure of the 20th century. What really made you believe, to everybody’s disbelief, that you could complete this impossible dream?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;05:14 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parce que la seule manière de réussir, c’est d’essayer. C’est vrai que je n’avais pas forcément beaucoup de chances a priori de réussir. Je venais du monde de l’aile delta de l’ULM, c’est vrai que j’avais gagné la course transatlantique en ballon avec un pilote belge, Thomas Straton, qui m’avait invité, donc, m’avait initié au ballon. Mais en même temps, les grands milliardaires qui voulaient être les premiers à faire le tour du monde en ballon avaient déjà construit leurs ballons et ils avaient déjà fait des tentatives, Richard Branson, Steve Fossett, pour en nommer que deux.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the only way to succeed, is to try. It’s true that I wasn’t necessarily having good a priori odds of success. I was coming from the world of delta-wing and UL gliding. It’s true that I had won the transatlantic balloon race with Belgian pilot, Thomas Straton, who had invited me. Therefore, I had been initiated in balloon. But at the same time, the big billionaires who wanted to be the first to make the balloon world-trip had already constructed their balloons and they had already made the attempts Richard Branson, Steve Fossett, to name just two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;05:45 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Puis moi, je me suis dit, mais, pourquoi pas moi finalement. Qu’est-ce que j’ai à perdre, si ce n’est d’essayer pour rien. Et finalement, la troisième tentative, j’ai réussi et j’ai fait le premier tour. Mais, pour moi, c’était vraiment une leçon de persévérance, d’apprentissage, de mener des très, très grands projets que tout le monde considérait impossible. Parce que c’est fou, vous vous confrontez à des gens qui se moquent de vous parce que vous ratez la première fois, qui vous disent que c’est de toute façon impossible, que vous n’y arriverez pas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But me, I told myself why not me really? I asked myself what do I have to lose, if not to try for nothing? And then, the third attempt, I succeeded and I completed the first circumnavigation. But for me, it’s really a lesson of perseverance, of learning, of carrying very very big projects that everyone considered impossible. Because it’s crazy you come across people who mock you because you failed the first time and they tell you that it’s in every way impossible and that you won’t make it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;06:14 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et c’est là que vous voyez finalement les gens qui sont des vrais pionniers et qui vous accompagnent. Et puis, tous ceux qui ont peur d’essayer quoi que ce soit et pour qui vous êtes une menace si vous réussissez.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s then that you finally see the the people who are the true pioneers and who will accompany you. As well as all those who are scared to try anything and who will see you as a threat if you succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;06:35 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Je crois que le souvenir le plus extraordinaire c’est le moment qu’il y a entre le décollage et l’atterrissage, c’est à dire les 20 jours eux-mêmes. Ça fait un tout, ça fait une espèce de rêve, ça fait un grand flash émotionnel, qui est teinté de toutes les couleurs qu’on a vues, de tous les paysages qu’on a vus. De tous les gens à qui on a parlé par radio. C’était vraiment un contact exceptionnel avec la planète et cela n’a pas été drôle tous les jours. Il y a eu des moments où c’était assez effrayants. Quand nous étions au-dessus du Pacifique, on s’approchait de l’Équateur et que nous n’avions presque plus de vent. Nous nous sommes perdus aussi dans le golfe du Mexique avec des vents qui étaient tout à fait défavorables pour nous. Et puis, chaque fois, il y a comme une main mystérieuse et invisible qui nous a remi dans la bonne direction et la bonne altitude pour permettre enfin de boucler ce tour.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I the most extraordinary souvenir is the moment between the takeoff and the landing. The 20 days themselves.  It makes complete, it makes a space for dreaming, it causes a great flash of emotion which is tinted with all the colours we saw, of all the landscapes that we saw. Of all the people I was speaking to on the radio. It was really an exceptional contact with the planet and it hasn’t been funny everyday. There were moments that were quite frightening. While over the Pacific, approaching the equator and there was very little wind. We were lost as well in the Gulf of Mexico with the winds that were all unfavorable for us. Then, each time, there is like a mysterious, invisible hand which sets us in the right direction and the right altitude allowing us to finally complete the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;07:25 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Il y a quelque chose de l’ordre du lâcher prise, de l’abandon profond aux éléments dans cette expérience de tour du monde en ballon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Qu’est ce qu’on ressent profondément, intimement, dans ces moments-là?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something about the act of letting go, about the deep helplessness to the elements during this experience of circling the world by balloon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it that you feel deeply, intimately in moments like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;07:37 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sur le plan technique, vous êtes dans un ballon qui doit voler trois semaines. Vous ne savez pas si le ballon va voler aussi longtemps, si vous avez assez de réserves de gaz. Si le vent va vous pousser dans la bonne direction pendant ces trois semaines. Mais en même temps, ce qui est magnifique, c’est que vous êtes poussés par les forces de la nature. Il n’y a pas de moteur, il n’y a pas de gouvernail. Vous êtes poussés par le vent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a technical level, you are in a balloon that must fly three weeks. You don’t know if the balloon is going to fly that long, or if you have enough gas reserves remaining. If the wind is going to push you in the right direction during these three week as well. But at the same time, what is wonderful, is that you are pushed by the forces of nature. There is no motor, no rudder. You are propelled by the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;07:55 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et puis, vous partez. Vous savez que vous avez 45 000 kilomètres en face de vous. Puis, peu à peu, vous arrivez à vous diriger et comment vous vous dirigez. Ce qui est extraordinaire, c’est que vous vous dirigez en changeant d’altitude parce que l’atmosphère est faite de couches météorologiques très différentes qui ont toutes une autre direction et une autre vitesse. Donc, si vous montez ou vous descendez, vous partez plus à gauche ou plus à droite et vous apprenez comme ça à utiliser ce changement d’altitude pour trouver la meilleure direction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you depart. You know that you have 45 000 kilometers in front of you. Well, little by little, you begin to gain control of yourself and your direction. What’s extraordinary, is that you manage your direction by changing altitude because the atmosphère is made of very different weather layers that all have different directions and speeds. Therefore, if you ascend or descend, you move more to the left or more to the right and you learn how to use the changing of altitude to find the best direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;08:22 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et pour changer d’altitude, vous devez lâcher du lest, lâcher du poids. et finalement, c’est une métaphore de la vie. C’est pour ça que j’aime le ballon. Le ballon, ce n’est pas un sport. Pour moi, c’est une philosophie de vie. Parce que dans la vie, vous êtes aussi poussé par les vents de la vie, par tout ce que vous ne pouvez pas contrôler, tout ce qui arrive, qui est en dehors de votre volonté souvent. Et vous devez lâcher du lest de vos certitudes, de vos habitudes, de vos dogmes, de vos croyances, de manière à pouvoir changer d’altitude et capter d’autres influences, d’autres directions dans laquelle la vie vous poussera.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to change the altitude, you need to let go of the ballast, to cast off the weight.  Finally, it’s a metaphor of life. It’s for this that I love the balloon. Ballooning is not a sport. For me, it’s a philosophy for life. Because in life, you are also pushed by the winds of life, all of which you cannot control, all of which arrive, which are outside of your will usually. And you need to let go of the ballast of your certainties, of your habits, of your dogmas, of your beliefs, in order to be able to change the attitude and pick up other influences, other directions in which life will push you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;09:05 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et puis, en 2003, vous vous êtes lancé dans le nouveau grand projet de votre existence avec la construction de Solar Impulse. Cet avion solaire capable de voler jour et nuit sans carburant. C’est à son bord que vous avez fait le tour du monde, de mars 2015 à juillet 2016. En vous relayant avec le pilote André Borschberg. Que cherchiez vous alors à prouver à vous-même et au monde?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, in 2003, you throw yourself into the next big project of your life with the construction of Solar Impulse. That solar airplane capable of flying day and night without fuel. It’s on board that you made the world tour, from March 2015 to July 2016. You along with the pilot André Borschberg, what were you seeking to prove to yourself and to the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;09:26 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quand j’ai atterri avec « Breitling Orbiter 3 » après le tour du monde en ballon, il restait 40 kilos de gaz liquide sur les 3700 kilos du départ.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I landed with Breitling Orbiter 3 after the world tour by balloon, It only had 40 kilos of liquid gas from the 3700 kilos on departure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;09:32 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous étiez vraiment sur le fil?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were really on the edge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;09:34 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On était vraiment sur le fil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really on the edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;09:36 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;C’est là que j’ai vu que quand on dit : « le ciel est la limite », « the sky is the limit », ce n’est pas vrai, c’est le carburant qui est la limite. Vous ne pouvez juste pas aller plus loin.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Après trois semaines, il restait deux heures d’autonomie, et c’est là que j’ai commencé à rêver d’une possibilité de faire un tour du monde sans carburant et d’utiliser ça pour montrer ce qu’on peut faire en libérant du pétrole, ce qu’on peut faire avec des technologies propres, ce qu’on peut faire avec des énergies renouvables en termes d’exploits a priori impossibles. 
C’était ça qui me motivait alors dans Solar Impulse. Donc ce n’était pas de dire que tout le monde allait voler avec des avions solaires prochainement mais que cet avion pouvait être un messager, un ambassadeur des énergies renouvelables et montrer que si on pouvait le faire en vol, là où c’est le plus difficile, et bien forcément, on peut le faire au sol aussi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s there that I saw that when they say ‘the sky that is the limit’ it’s not true.  It’s the fuel that is the limit.   You just can’t go further.
After 3 weeks, what remained was two hours of runnning. and it’s there that I started to dream of the possibility to make a world tour without fuel and using that to show what can be done free from petroleum.  What can be done with renewable energy and what  we can do with renewable energies in terms of a priori exploits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that which motivated me towards Solar Impulse at that time.  It wasn’t to claim that everybody is going to fly with solar airplanes soon, but that this airplane can be a messenger and an ambassador of renewable energy and show what can be done in flight where it’s more difficult so it can be done on the ground as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10:25 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous aviez eu peur pendant ce moment-là?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re you scared at that time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10:26 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Je n’ai jamais eu peur en vol. Parce qu’en vol, on est tellement connecté à soi-même, on est dans un tel niveau de performance, de conscience qu’on a l’impression qu’on arrive à résoudre les différents problèmes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Par contre, j’ai eu très souvent peur au sol, de ne pas pouvoir voler, de ne pas aboutir avec cette aventure, on était plusieurs fois à deux mois de la faillite parce que c’était quand-même une aventure où il fallait payer une centaine de personnes en moyenne tous les mois.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Donc il fallait des sponsors, des partenaires, pour que ça marche. Il fallait que l’avion vol bien, on avait des problèmes météo, des problèmes techniques, énormément de problèmes administratifs et bureaucratiques, terribles. Donc, tout ça c’était très lourd et je dois dire que c’était fatigant, c’était pénible. il fallait beaucoup de résilience, heureusement il y avait les moments de vol qui eux étaient extraordinaires.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been scared in flight.  Because in flight, I am so connected to myself and am in such a level of peformance and awareness that I’m ready to resolve various problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I was often afraid on the ground, of not being able to fly, of not being able to complete this adventure.  There were several times we were two months  from bankruptcy because it was still an venture which needed to pay a hundred people on average each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore we needed sponsors &amp;amp; partners to proceed. We needed a plane that flies well.  There were weather problems, technical problems large administrative and bureaucratic problems.  Therefore it was all very onerous and I must say, it was tiring and painful.  It took a lot of resilience.  Fortunately, there were moments in my flight that were extraordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11:15 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous pourriez nous raconter un petit peu ces moments-là?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you tell us a little bit about these moments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11:18 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous êtes aligné sur une piste de décollage dans un aéroport, quel qu’il soit, en Chine, en Birmanie, aux États-Unis. Vous avez toute votre équipe autour de l’avion, les membres de l’équipe tiennent les ailes, vous avez une partie des ingénieurs à Monaco qui communiquent par téléphone satellite avec vous.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous êtes comme dans un lancement de fusée, pratiquement, et puis tout à coup, vous avez la tour de contrôle qui vous dit: « Solar Impulse 2 vous êtes autorisés au décollage ». Et là vous mettez des manettes des moteurs à fond, il n’y a pas bruit, un tout petit sifflement. Vous avez l’avion qui commence à avancer et au bout de 150 mètres vous êtes en l’air. Alors, ça ne monte pas comme une fusée, ca monte très doucement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are lined up at any takeoff runway in China, Burma, US.  You have all your aircraft team around the plane. The members of the team hold the wings.  You have a party of engineers in monaco who communicate with you via satellite phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like launching a rocket really. The suddenly you have the control tower which tells you: “Solar Impulse 2 that you are cleared to take-off”.  Then you apply the full throttle to the motors, there is no sound, just a small whistle. You have the plane beginning to advance until after 150m, you are in the air. So it doesn’t climb like a rocket, it climbs very slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12:00 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mais il n’y a pas bruit, il n’y a pas de carburant, il n’y a pas de pollution, et vous êtes dans un avion totalement unique au monde, et vous vous dites:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;« Et bien voilà, j’ai décollé. Maintenant, j’ai l’Atlantique devant moi, j’ai le Pacifique devant moi, j’ai la Chine devant moi »;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;que vous savez que vous allez rester en vol plusieurs jours et plusieurs nuits, et que vous êtes au milieu de l’inconnue, au milieu des doutes, au milieu de tas choses qui vont peut-être ne pas se passer comme vous voulez, et vous devez réussir. Moi, je me rappelle très bien quand j’ai laissé la cote de Hawaii derrière mois et que j’avais 4000 kilomètres d’eau jusqu’à San Francisco, c’est extraordinaire comme moment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s no noise and there’s no fuel and no pollution. You are in a plane that is totally unique in the world and you to yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Voila, I’ve launched.  Now, I have the Atlantic in front of me, I have the Pacific in front of me.  I have China in front of me.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that you know that you are going to stay in flight many days and nights.  and you are in a milieu of thoughts, of doubts, of many things that may not happen the way you want and you must succeed. Me, I remember very well when I left the coast of Hawaii behind me and I had 4000 kms of water until San Francisco. It was an extraordinary moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12:38 - Reporter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dans le ciel, seules quelques lumières trouent l’obscurité. En silence, Solar Impulse 2 est apparu au-dessus de l’aéroport d’Abou Dabi. L’avion solaire, se pose très lentement. Sur le tarmac, André Borschberg accueille son coéquipier Bertrand Piccard, ils se congratulent. Leur pari insensé est gagné.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sky, just a few lights pierce the darkness.  In silence, Solar Impulse II appears over Abu Dhabi airort.  The solar plane lands very slowly. On the tarmac, Andre Bourgberg embraces his teammate Bertrand Piccard. The congratulate each other.  The insane bet is won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13:04 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Je voudrais vous faire lire un petit passage d’une de vos citations qui résume votre conception enthousiaste et métaphysique de l’aventure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;alors c’est celle-ci&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like you to read a small passage of one of your quotes that summarizes your enthusiastic and metaphysical concept of adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is it here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13:17 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;L’aventure est un état d’esprit vis-à-vis de l’inconnu une façon de concevoir notre existence comme un chant expérimental dans lequel nous sommes obligés de développer une ressource intérieure, de gravir le chemin de l’évolution personnelle et d’assimiler les valeurs éthiques et spirituelles dont nous avons besoin comme compagnon de voyage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adventure is a spiritual state facing the unknown. A manner of conceiving our existence like an experimental song in which we are required to develop an interior resource, of climbing the path of personal evolution and of assimilating the ethics and spiritual values within that we need like a travelling companion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13:44 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Est-ce que vous pourriez me dire un peu comment ont évolué, justement, ces ressources intérieures que vous avez su mobiliser depuis vos premières expériences de vol en delta-plane à aujourd’hui.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could you tell me a bit on exactly how these interior resources that you have mobilized since your first experiences before with hang-gliding have evolved until today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13:55 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Au début c’était le courage et c’est devenu la confiance. Le courage c’est quand vous arrivez à faire quelque chose même si vous avez peur. Mais ce n’est pas suffisant. Moi ce que je remarque, c’est que ce qui important c’est la confiance. Et c’est ce que j’ai prouvé quand j’étais avec Breitling Orbiter 3, entre terre et ciel, avec Solar Impulse 2, au milieu d’un océan, vous êtes tout seul, vous êtes là, même de nuit, à des milliers de kilomètres de toute possibilité de secours et vous vous sentez mieux que dans tous les moments de votre vie normale.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it was the courage and then came the confidence.  The courage is when you will proceed to do something even if you are scared.  But that’s not enough.  What I noticed, is that what matters is confidence and that’s what I proved when I with Brietling Orbiter 3, between earth and sky, and with Solar Impulse 2.  Within the vastness of the ocean, you are all alone, even at night and thousands of kilometers away from all possibilities of relief and you feel better than at any time in your normal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14:28 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et ça au début, c’était vraiment un point d’interrogation, je me disais, mais comment c’est possible, je suis complètement fou, je suis dans une situation qui empêcherait tout le monde de dormir et moi je me sent mieux que dans n’importe quel moment de ma vie. 
Et en fait, je crois que c’est vraiment le fait que quand on se met en rupture par rapport à toutes nos habitudes tout notre conditionnement qu’on est catapulté en dehors de sa zone de confort en est obligé de se retrouver à l’intérieur de soi-même et d’aller puiser les ressources qu’il vous faut au fond de soi-même. Et quand vous trouvez les ressources qu’il vous faut en vous, ça donne une confiance immense dans l’être humain, dans la vie, dans le monde, dans tout ce qui nous guide, parce qu’on voit qu’on a en soi ce qu’il faut pour avancer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the beginning, it was really a question mark.  I was telling myself, but how is it possible, I’m completely crazy.  I am in a situation that would prevent everyone from sleeping and I feel better than any time in my life. 
In effect, I believe that it’s really the fact that when we break from all our conditioning, that we are catapulted out of our comfort zone, we are forced to find our true selves and when we find the resources that we need within ourselves, it gives an immense confidence in humanity; in life; in the world; in all that guides us because we see in ourselves everything that is needed to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15:10 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mais est-ce que vous appréhendez les atterrissages, la manière de se réacclimater au monde au sol&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do you prepared yourself for the landing, the way to reacclimatize to the world on the ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15:15 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;L’avantage c’est que quand vous êtes vraiment dans ces moments de grâce, quand vous voyez à quel point vous pouvez fonctionner mieux que d’habitude, quand vous revenez dans la vie normale, la vie n’est plus totalement normale. Vous arrivez à en extraire beaucoup plus de l’essentiel. Vous arrivez à donner beaucoup plus de valeur aux relations humaines, au destin, à la spiritualité, à tous les événements de la vie. Vous voyez qu’en fait l’aventure elle n’est pas que « en l’air », l’aventure elle est aussi au sol. Elle est dans votre vie de tous les jours dans tout ce qui guide vos pas à la recherche de ce que vous cherchez.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great thing is that when you are really in these moments of grace, when you see at what point you can function better than usual. When you return to normal life, life is no longer completely normal. You come to get a lot more out of the essentials. You come to place a lot more value on human relationships, to fate, to spirituality, to all the stages in life.  You see that in fact the deventure is not just in the air.  The adventure is also on the ground.  It is in your everyday life and in everything that guides you towards what you are seeking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16:04 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Une autre facette de votre vie que nous n’avons pas encore explorée, mais vous avez donc décidé de faire des études de médecine avec une double spécialisation en psychiatrie et psychothérapie, qu’est-ce que vous avez tiré de tous ces apprentissages sur les mondes intérieurs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of your life that we haven’t already explored, you have done decided to study medicine with a double specialization in psychiatry and psychotherapy.  What have you pulled from all these studies about the interior world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16:18 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;J’ai vu à quel point les gens souffrent et se sentent mal dans leur vie. Au moment où ils oublient leur racine spirituelle, au moment où ils ont perdu le sens du contexte dans lequel ils vivent. Beaucoup de gens veulent se rassurer avec des repères extérieurs, très matériels, s’appuient sur des gens qu’ils aiment mais qui peuvent mourir, sur de l’argent qui peut disparaître, et finalement je pense qu’il y a énormément de gens qui sont angoissés parce qu’ils vivent en équilibre instable sur des repères qui peuvent s’effondrer à n’importe quel moment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw to what point people suffer and feel bad in their lives. At the time they forget their spiritual roots. At the moment where they have lost the sense of context in which they live.  Many people want to comfort themselves with external, very material fixes/benchmarks.  To rely on people they love but who can die or over money which can disappear. Finally I think that there are many people who are disoriented because they live in unstable equilibrium based on landmarks that could collapse at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17:00 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ce qui est fondamental, c’est de développer le sens de l’essentiel. C’est à dire Revenir à pourquoi on vit, et se dire que peut-être qu’on vient de quelque part, mais on ne sait pas où. On va quelque part, et on ne sait pas où. On ne sait pas très bien pourquoi on est là. Et au lieu d’avoir des réponses toutes faites, on peut se permettre d’avoir des questions ouvertes. Et quand on a des questions ouvertes, on devient un explorateur.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s fundamental, is to develop a sence of the essential. I mean to return to the why of life and say to ourselves that maybe we come from somewhere, but we don’t know where.  We are going somewhere, but we don’t know where We don’t really know why we are here.  So instead of having answers for everything, we can allow for open questions. and when you have open questions, you become an explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17:24 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mais est-ce que ce n’est pas épuisant d’être sans cesse dans ce mouvement de renouvellement, de grand questionnement existentiel?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But isn’t it exhausting to be constantly in this movement of renewal? Of great existential questioning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17:29 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alors, moi je trouve que c’est ça qui nourrit, c’est ça qui donne l’énergie. Ce qui est épuisant c’est l’équilibre instable, se disant je ne sais pas pourquoi je vis, je ne sais pas ce que je fais là, mais il faut que je sois le plus heureux possible. Puis ensuite on fait comment pour être le plus heureux possible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alors, on essaie d’acquérir des biens matériels, d’être amoureux de quelqu’un qui n’est peut-être pas amoureux de vous. Enfin, il y a plein de choses qui ne dépendent plus de nous, alors que notre sécurité intérieure et notre quête, elles dépendent de nous. Et ça recadre complètement les événements qui arrivent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Les événements de la vie ne sont peut-être pas là pour vous détruire, les événements de la vie sont peut-être là pour vous stimuler à lâcher des certitudes, lâcher des habitudes, lâcher des croyances, vous ouvrir à d’autres dimensions et trouver d’autres influences qui vont vous emmener dans d’autres directions de votre vie.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I find that it’s what nourishes.  It’s that which gives the energy.  What is exhausting, is the unstable equilibrium.  If I don’t know why I’m alive, I don’t know what I’m doing here. But I should be as happy as possible.  So what can be done to be as happy as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we try to acquire material goods, to be in love with someone who is not in love with you. Finally, there are plenty of things that don’t depend on us anymore.  And they completely reframe the events that come along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe life events don’t happen to destroy you.  Maybe life events happen to stimulate you to release the certainties, to release the habits, release the beliefs, to open up other dimensions and find influences that will take your life in new directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18:16 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et vous trouvez que la société est réceptive à ce discours-là ? On voit qu’il y a un changement de paradigme et une prise de conscience de ça aujourd’hui?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And do you find that society is receptive to this discours? Does there appear to be a paradigm shift and consciousness like that today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18:22 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moi j’ai toujours observé que l’évolution elle se faisait beaucoup plus à titre individuel que collectivement. Je n’ai pas l’impression que c’est la société qui évolue dans cette direction-là. Ce sont les individus isolément qui tout à coup trouvent quelque chose là-dedans qui leur permet d’avancer. On ne vit pas dans une société qui s’intéresse à l’essentiel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me, I have always observed that the evolution more individually than collectively.  I don’t have the impression that society is developing in this direction. It’s these isolated individuals who have suddenly found something that gives them the ability to advance.  We don’t live in a society that is interested in the essentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18:50 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous l’avez brièvement évoqué tout à l’heure, mais vous avez grandi dans une famille aussi très portée sur la spiritualité avec une grand-mère maternelle pasteure. Votre mère aussi qui vous a fait part de ses études sur le bouddhisme sur le taoïsme. Comment est-ce que ça a nourri votre parcours?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You briefly mentioned it earlier. But you grew up in a family that was very spiritual with a maternal grandmother who was a pastor. Your mother as well who imparted you with her studies of buddhism and Taoism.  How has this nourished your journey?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;19:04 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;C’est un aspect fondamental, et d’habitude, tout le monde me parle de mon père et de mon grand-père, qui sont des explorateurs qui ont apporté énormément au 20ème siècle, mais c’est vrai qu’avoir une mère qui vous prend au sérieux comme enfant, dans votre recherche de compréhension de la vie, de la mort, de Dieu, des autres, c’est extraordinaire.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;J’ai passé des heures et des heures à me promener avec ma mère dans la forêt, dans la montagne, un peu partout, déjà quand j’avais 6 ans, 7 ans, et puis je lui posais toutes les questions que je pouvais pour essayer de comprendre pourquoi j’étais là, à quoi ça sert tout ce qu’on fait, tout ce qu’on voit, on vient d’où, on va où, et cetera.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Puis elle m’expliquait tout ce qu’elle avait compris dans toutes ses recherches. Que ce soit dans le christianisme, dans le bouddhisme, dans l’hindouisme, dans tous les groupes de développement personnel, et cetera. Et puis de temps en temps elle me disait : « ha bah ça, je ne sais pas ». Mais c’est extraordinaire comme cadeau quand un adulte dit à un enfant : « je ne sais pas ».&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a fundamental aspect and usually everyone talks to me about my father and grandfather, who were explorers that contributed alot to the 20th century. But it’s really my mother who  takes you seriously as a child in attempting to understand life, death, God, others. It’s extraordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent hours and hours walking with my mother in the forest, in the mountains everywhere. Already when I was 6 to 7 years old, I would ask all these questions that I could. Trying To try and understand why I was there, what is the point of everything we do, everything we see, we come from where, we go where, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then she explained to me all that she understood from her research.  Whether in Christianity, in Buddhism, in Hinduism in different personal development groups. And sometimes she would say to me: “I don’t know”. But it’s an amazing gift to a child when an adult says: “I don’t know”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20:02 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oui, l’honnêteté de savoir avouer ses limites aussi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the honesty of knowing how to admit your limits as well&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20:06 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mais totalement, l’honnêteté absolue et puis en plus la stimulation pour l’enfant de se dire : « Mes parents ne savent pas, mais moi je vais peut-être essayer de comprendre et essayer de trouver. » Donc ça donne envie d’aller plus loin, ce ne sont plus seulement des questions, ça devient une quête. Alors j’avais la quête de comprendre le monde intérieur avec ma mère, de comprendre le monde extérieur avec mon père, et c’est en fait la synthèse des deux qui m’a animé toute ma vie.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ya totally, absolute honesty and then on top of that the stimulation for the child. To say to themself, “My parents don’t know but me i’m going to try to understand and try to find out”.  It’s more than just questions now. It has become a quest.  So I had the quest to understand the interior world with my mother and the exterior world with my father.  and it is really the synthesis of both that has animated me all my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20:28 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On comprend pourquoi vous êtes aussi, comme un équilibriste, toujours entre ces deux grands domaines de recherche. Vous-même, est-ce qu’aujourd’hui vous vous définiriez comme croyant, je crois que vous avez éduqué vos filles dans la religion catholique.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understanding why you are also, like a balancing artist, always in between these two great areas of research.  You are, today, what you would define as a believer.  I believe that you have educated your daughter in the Catholic religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20:40 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oui, alors croyant, cela dépend en quoi. Moi, je ne crois pas dans le dieu que les hommes ont fabriqué pour se rassurer de leur peur de la mort. Par contre, je crois en un dieu qui a créé l’être humain. Et qui, pour une raison qu’on ne connait pas très bien, a manifesté toute cette création, je pense qu’il y a un créateur à tout ça, je pense qu’il y a quelque chose qui donne un sens.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Donc ce qui m’intéresse le plus c’est la notion de transcendance. C’est la notion d’une force supérieure, d’une énergie supérieure qui donne un sens à ce qu’on vit. Mais effectivement, on ne le comprend pas parce qu’on n’est pas à ce niveau, et je pense que l’être humain ne peux pas mettre un visage à Dieu, attribuer des émotions ou des volontés à Dieu, c’est horriblement présomptueux et arrogant de dire Dieu est comme si, Dieu est comme ça. On n’en sait rien, on doit être Dieu pour comprendre Dieu. C’est déjà difficile de connaître les hommes quand on est homme. Donc vous voyez…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, on believing, it depends on what.  Me, I don’t believe in the God that people have fabricated in order to reassure themselves about their fear of death.  On the contrary, I believe in one God who created the human being.  Who, for some reason that we don’t understand well, manifested all of creation.  I believe that there is a creator behind it all. I think there’s something that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore what interests me most is the notion of transcendence.  It’s the notion of a higher force, a higher energy that gives a meaning to what we experience as life. But effectively, it’s incomprehensible because it’s on a different level and I think that humans cannot put a face to God, attribute emotions or wills to God, It’s horribly presumptuous and arrogant to say God is like this or God is like that. It’s already hard to understand people when you are a person. So you see…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21:44 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;L’an dernier, vous avez aussi rencontré le pape François au Vatican. Est-ce que vous pourriez nous raconter cette rencontre?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year you also met Pope Francis at the Vatican.  Could you tell us about that meeting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21:50 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moi j’avais envie de rencontrer le pape François parce que… en fait c’est le premier pape que j’avais envie de rencontrer. Parce que j’ai l’impression que c’est le premier que s’est vraiment occupé des grands problèmes de notre monde : la pauvreté, l’environnement, le respect entre les êtres humains ; et qui essaie d’améliorer la qualité de vie sur Terre, indépendamment de toute politique.
Et puis j’avais lu le « laudato si » qui est cette encyclique sur l’environnement. Et j’avais envie de lui en parler parce qu’en fait, ce « laudato si », il très intéressant pour ceux qui arrivent à le compredre. Mais quand on parle essentiellement de respect pour l’environnement, d’amour pour le prochain et de reconnaissance pour la création divine, on va toucher une certaine partie des gens et ceux qu’on touche ne sont pas ceux qui détruisent l’environnement.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to meet with Pope Francis because, actually he is the first Pope I wanted to meet.  Because I have the impression that he’s the first who is really occupied with the great problems of our world like poverty, environment, respect between people; and who is trying to improve the quality of life on Earth independently of politics.
And then I read the Laudato Si which is the encyclical about the environment. and I had wanted to talk because really that Laudato Si is very interesting for those who manage to understand it.  But when we mainly speak about respect for the environment, love for thy neighbour and gratitude for divine creation, it will touch a certain group of people and those it touches are not those who destroy the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;22:35 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ce n’est pas ceux qui tuent, torturent et massacrent leurs semblables.  Par conséquent, j’avais envie de lui dire, mais quel est la language qu’il faut pour convaincre ceux qui ne sont pas encore convaincus. Et moi j’avais envie d’aborder avec lui ce… C’est de ça qu’on a parlé, de toutes les solutions technologiques qui sont financièrement rentables et qui peuvent protéger l’environnement. Même quand on est égoïste, même quand on n’est pas spirituel ou religieux, même quand on a aucun respect pour les autres, mais peut-être qu’on peut faire du bien quand même parce qu’on y trouve un avantage soi-même.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not those who kill, torture and massacre their fellow human beings. That’s why I had wanted to speak with him but what is the language that can convince those who aren’t already convinced? I wanted to approach this with him. That’s what we talked about, all of these technological solutions that are financially profitable and can protect the environment.  Even when you are selfish, even when you are not spiritual or religious even if you have no respect for others but maybe you can still do good because there is an advantage for your own self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23:10 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous pensez la technologie pourrait sauver le monde?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you think technology can save the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23:13 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;La technologie, ça dépend ce qu’on en fait. On peut détruire le monde avec la technologie, on peut sauver le monde avec la technologie. Mais aujourd’hui, c’est clair qu’il y a des technologies propres qui permettent à l’être humain d’être beaucoup plus efficient, d’économiser de l’énergie, d’économiser des ressources naturelles, économiser de la nourriture, valoriser les déchets, fonctionner nettement mieux et aujourd’hui vous avez en tout cas la moitié du problème qui resolvable totalement grâce à la technologie : technologies propres et énergies renouvelables. 
L’autre moitié nécessitera forcément des aménagements économiques, des aménagements d’attitude, de comportement humain, mais il ne faut pas commencer par le comportement humain, parce que si vous dites aux gens de faire des sacrifices, ils vont prendre l’écologie en grippe. Si vous leur dites, vous pouvez continuer à faire la même chose mais vous pouvez avoir un impact divisé par dix sur l’environnement parce que vous serez plus efficients, les technologies modernes vous permettront de protéger l’environnement. Et bien ils vont adorer l’écologie. Par conséquent, il faut commencer par faire tout ce qu’on peut sur le plan technologique, et puis ensuite, si on doit aller plus loin, à ce moment-là, on peut peut-être demander aux gens de changer les attitudes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology depends on how it is used.  We can destroy the world with technology and we can save the world with technology.  But today it’s clear that there is the right technology to permit humanity to be a lot more efficient. More energy efficiency, efficiency of natural resources, food efficiency and increasing the value of waste that function better and today you have in any cases half of the problems that can be solved thanks to technology: Clean technology and renewable energy.&lt;br /&gt;
The other half requires economic adjustments, as well as adjustment to attitudes and human behaviours. But it shouldn’t start with human behaviour because when you are asking people to make sacrifices.  They are going to take ecology into consideration.  If you tell them, you  can continue doing the same thing but you can have 10% of the environmental impact because you are more efficient, modern technologies permit you to protect the environment. Then they are going to love the ecology. Therefore we should start by doing everything we can with technology. Then if we must go further, perhaps we can people to change their attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24:20 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Et le pape François été réceptif à votre discours pendant votre rencontre?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Pope Francis was receptive to your speech during your meeting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24:24 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On a dit qu’on allait se revoir, mais c’était un mois avant le début de la pandémie quand je l’ai rencontré. Donc c’est vrai qu’on n’a pas pu se revoir. On a gardé des contacts épistolaires, notamment avec le cardinal Turkson qui dirige cette partie-là du Vatican. Je me réjouis de pouvoir aller lui amener les milles solutions rentables pour protéger l’environnement que la fondation Solar Impulse saura trouver d’ici le mois d’avril et de pouvoir lui montrer qu’il y a énormément de technologies qui peuvent motiver, dans la protection de l’environnement, ceux qui ne sont pas sensibles à son « laudato si ».&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We said that we would meet again. But it was a month before the start of the epidemic when we met. So really we haven’t had the chance to meet again.  We’ve kept in written contact, especially with Cardinal Turkson who directs that part of the Vatican.  I’m thrilled to be able to bring him the 1000 profitable solutions to protect the environment that the Solar Impulse Foundation will be able to find by April and to be able to show him that there are many technologies that can motivate, towards protection of the environment, those who are not sensitive to his Laudato Si.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24:58 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comment est-ce que vous vous situez par rapport à une certaine écologie catastrophiste et millénariste?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you position yourself in relation to a certain catastrophist and millenarian ecology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;25:05 - BP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pour que les gens adoptent de nouvelles solutions, adoptent de nouvelles technologies, passent du pétrole au solaire, passent du chauffage inefficient à la pompe à chaleur, passent d’une voiture diesel à une voiture électrique. En fait, il faut un choc, parce que sinon, il n’y a pas grand monde qui a l’esprit de pionnier et qui est intéressé spontanément par le changement. Et ce choc, les écologistes le donnent, les catastrophistes le donnent, Greta Thunnberg le donne, et c’est bien, parce qu’il faut que les gens voient que s’ils ne font rien, on court tous à la catastrophe. Et la catastrophe va venir beaucoup plus vite qu’on ne le croit et de manière beaucoup plus grave qu’on ne le croit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Par contre, il y a des solutions pour éviter cette catastrophe. Et si on a peur de la catastrophe, on va se mobiliser beaucoup plus pour utiliser des solutions et changer le cours des choses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people to adopt new solutions, adopt new technologies, switch from petrol to solar, switch from inefficient heating to heat pumps switch from a diesel car to an electric.  In fact, requires a shock.  Because otherwise not many people are pioneering and spontaneously interested in changing.  It’s this shock the ecologists give, that the catastrophits give, that Greta Thornburg gives. It’s good because people have to see that if they do nothing, everyone is headed for a disaster and the disaster will come a lot more quickly and seriously than most believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are solutions for avoiding the catastrophe.  If we are afraid of the catastrophes, and if we are afraid of the disaster, we will mobilize much more to use these solutions to change the course of things&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;25:58 - MT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vous venez d’écouter un épisode de la troisième saison de « Place des Religions ». S’il vous a intéressé, n’hésitez pas à le partager et à vous abonner à notre podcast. « Place des Religions » est à écouter sur toutes les plateformes, sur le site et l’appli « La Croix ».&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have just listened to an episode of the third season of “Place des Religions”. If it interested you, feel free to share it and subscribe to our podcast. “Place des Religions” can be listened to on all platforms, on the “La Croix” website and app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;houseofswitzerland.org/sites/default/files/story/gallery/2014_10_28_18th_Flight_Pizzolante_Solar_Impulse_2_8_web.jpg&quot;&gt;houseofswitzerland.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="solar-impulse" /><summary type="html">Last month, Capt Piccard sat down with the Malo Tresca and the podcast Place des Religions for a discussion about exploration, consciousness and how the Solar Impulse Network of 1000 Solutions can contribute to the great existential challenge of the 21st century. I decided to do a translation into English. I opted to do this for a few reasons: Just for fun and French practice To reflect more on where Solar Impulse might be heading with its newest initiative and tagline Ecology as driving force for economy I really want to see this initiative succeed</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sunE declares intention to achieve Net-Zero across its supply chain by 2025.</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/announcements/declaration-to-achieve-net-zero/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sunE declares intention to achieve Net-Zero across its supply chain by 2025." /><published>2021-08-24T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-08-24T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/announcements/declaration-to-achieve-net-zero</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/announcements/declaration-to-achieve-net-zero/">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce a minor (but important) change in compass-heading for the sunE Venture.  Please see our declaration to achieve net-zero &lt;a href=&quot;/sunE-net-zero-declaration/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="announcements" /><summary type="html">We are pleased to announce a minor (but important) change in compass-heading for the sunE Venture. Please see our declaration to achieve net-zero here</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Past, Present and Future of Environmentalism - Presentation for Mapua’s Social Sciences and Education week</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/presentations/environmentalism/mapua-humanities-presentation-environmentalism-past-present-future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Past, Present and Future of Environmentalism - Presentation for Mapua’s Social Sciences and Education week" /><published>2021-06-26T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-06-26T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/presentations/environmentalism/mapua-humanities-presentation-environmentalism-past-present-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/presentations/environmentalism/mapua-humanities-presentation-environmentalism-past-present-future/">&lt;p&gt;As part the week in Social Sciences and Education at &lt;a href=&quot;ssse.mapua.edu.ph&quot;&gt;Mapua University&lt;/a&gt;, I was grateful for the opportunity to share my thoughts about environmentalism with some of the bright, emerging minds of the Philippines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/mapua-ssed-presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;Please click here to access: Past, Present and Future for Environmentalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attempted to share what I felt was a good cross-section of links and references which represent the evolution of my own views since &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ualberta.ca/catalogue/course/ren_r/260&quot;&gt;taking a similar course&lt;/a&gt; during my own time spent in university.  I suspect more robust references could be found within the walls of academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that what I shared will help give some students ideas on how to forge their own path in the world and find the courage to pursue their passion in a field as dynamic and complex as environmental sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readers are asked to please be mindful that the contents of this presentation were delivered with an addtional oral explanation so there is potential to misinterpret the statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome respectful discussion on this and I recognize that some of the topics discussed inside may have alterantive explanations that are also valid.  Meanwhile I will also contend that there are plenty of messages and opinions that we (humanity) have adopted which give a comfortable position from which to continue our destructive tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has been made, but we still have lots of work ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opinions expressed in this presentation should not be considered as representative of the broader sunE team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mapua/mapua-ssed-poster.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Social Sciences and Eduation - Mapua&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="environmentalism" /><summary type="html">As part the week in Social Sciences and Education at Mapua University, I was grateful for the opportunity to share my thoughts about environmentalism with some of the bright, emerging minds of the Philippines. Please click here to access: Past, Present and Future for Environmentalism</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Pedal Powered Adventure - An hommage to Piccard’s Epic Voyage</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/my-pedal-powered-journey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Pedal Powered Adventure - An hommage to Piccard’s Epic Voyage" /><published>2021-04-12T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/my-pedal-powered-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/my-pedal-powered-journey/">&lt;p&gt;In a salute to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/beyond-1000-solutions&quot;&gt;1000 solution milestone&lt;/a&gt; of the Solar Impulse Foundation, This story is a bit of an hommage to the immensely inspiring 2010 TED talk by Captain Bertrand Piccard titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/bertrand_piccard_my_solar_powered_adventure#t-1046442&quot;&gt;‘My Solar-Powered Adventure’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entrepreneurship adventure of ours has had many highs and lows.  His speech has pulled me out of the depths of despair on more than one occasion.  What a great gift to humanity he has given by providing a living embodiment for the &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/next_generation.jpg&quot;&gt;Next Generation&lt;/a&gt; to tackle one of the biggest challenges of our time.  The team at sunE couldn’t be prouder to have been accepted onto this ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-without-further-ado-onto-the-story&quot;&gt;So without further ado, onto the story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year is 2011, I had just won best presentation award at the 1st Student Research Symposium of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.helmholtz-alberta.org/?page_id=109&quot;&gt;Helmholtz Alberta Initiative&lt;/a&gt;.  As the only undergaduate to participate in the event, how exciting it was to be recognized by such accomplished academics for my efforts in trying to understand the nature of the energy tucked away deep below our feet.  I asked of one of these men, the head of an experimental forest in Germany, what is my next step?  His answer was simple:
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/science_handout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Just put your hand out&quot; /&gt;
	“Just put your hand out.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the answer I was looking for.  During my studies, I had formed the opinion that if we are going to solve climate change, it will be because we figured out how to make the business work.  Besides, I’d just graduated and spent the last couple months touring around southern British Columbia with one of my best buds Frankie (a master baker, painter and one of the most wonderfully caring souls you’ll ever meet).  I was in adventure mode and keen to bike down to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icenews.is/2011/10/23/geothermal-energy-conference-to-see-participation-from-islandsbanki/&quot;&gt;Geothermal Resources Convention&lt;/a&gt; in California.  With all the volcanoes along the way, I was super excited about all the new things I would discover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had stars in my eyes, I was on cloud-9.  Before I left, I stopped in to see my buddy Frankie, he was not looking so good.  Now that summer was over, he didn’t know how we was gonna make ends meet and didn’t know who to turn to.  He asked for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I was, on one side, being given the opportunity to write my dream ticket.  On the other side, with a close friend desperately seeking a hand which I had no idea how to give.  But my bags were packed, I was hitting the road.  I cut the ballast, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I picked up a ‘commuter’ bike (I was on my way to find a job after all) and a bit of camping gear from Lethbridge, Alberta and hit the road.
This is the picture of my border crossing.  Of course, in earlier times, there was no border and this was known simply as Blackfoot territory.  But I was happy to give a salute to all 3 nations represented at the border that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/border.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Montana border crossing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaves and huckleberry pies of Montana in the autumn are a special treat that few know about.  The mountains aren’t as jagged as the peaks to the north in Canada, but the rivers wind through those valleys like the crispest ribbons of silk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less than an hour across the border, BEAR!  BIG F-ING BEAR!  Biggest bloody grizzly bear I’ve ever seen in my life.  Bigger than most pickup trucks, I’m pretty sure with its paws stretched out, it would have spanned the entire 2-lane highway.  Less than 100 meters in front of me and my little commuter. This picture is not the actual bear by the way, I just found it on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/grizzly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BIG F-ING BEAR!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I grew up in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.climatehotmap.org/global-warming-locations/british-columbia-canada.html&quot;&gt;Prince George&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve seen some big grizzly bears before.  But this was something else.  I didn’t even know they could get that big!!  But he didn’t stop, so he was gone as quickly as he appeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On I went, into the Snake River Plane..volcano and ice cave territory.  I came upon a geology book with a fascinating theory.  That around 17 million years ago a meteor hit the crust so hard, that it cracked right down to the mantle and up came the volcanic hotspot we now know today as Yellowstone. 
Around the same time, Nevada stared stretching apart like a piece of taffy.  This created all sorts of volcanic goodies like hot springs, geothermal reservoirs and lithium deposits (a bit of gold and copper as well, if you’re into that sort of thing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/nevada_rifting.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nevada Rifting!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I can tell, that particular theory didn’t really &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-03-19-me-477-story.html&quot;&gt;gain acceptance&lt;/a&gt; within the academic community to date.  I’m sure many alternate explanations are also very compelling, but that one has always stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Northern Nevada is a pretty rugged place.  Some like to joke that the only water around is boiling hot. It’s also a place for treasure hunters.  Probably one of the reasons the casinos felt so at home in the early days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One morning, after a night spent befriending a group of local bikers at Farpoint Station, I heard them calling out to me.  They were worried but relieved when I came from my camp.  They showed me all of the fresh mountain lion tracks around my bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/cougar_paw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My, what big claws you have!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that day on, I slept wearing my bike helmet, with bike chain around my neck, and buck knife in hand. Thankfully, I made it into California with no more feline encounters and time to spare.  I even got to hop in some top-notch natural hotsprings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/hot_spring.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Best bath ever!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, at the conference, pretty much everyone told me that I would need to go back to school to find a way into that industry.  I suppose that made sense.  But while speaking to the director of a major power company, I also received what I would now consider my first piece of executive advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Don’t feel bad being a big fish in a small pond”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thesis mentor, Jacek also came out.  He told me about the great priviledge that comes from the attaining of a PhD and that I would probably benefit from the stability that universities can provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/jacek.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;me n Jacek&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then the trip was over, even if I wasn’t going to have my big break into the clean energy industry just yet, I was still supercharged from the experience and I was sure I would do it…somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flight back to Canada, I got a phone call.  Frankie was dead… Just like that, my world changed.  For all of the potential that I could look forward to, I had failed one of my closest friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/frankie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frankie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suicide is a complex issue at the best of times.  Everybody will have their thoughts about what could have been done.  Family &amp;amp; friends will each have different memories. Warning signs. Silent cries for help. 
“Oh, what I would have done if only I’d known.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, there cry for help was not silent.  It was the last conversation that I had with him.  I chose not to act and I will carry that with me for the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This achieving the centre - being grounded in one’s self - is about the highest state a human being can achieve” - Bruce Lee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we decided to move to the Philippines to start sunE, it was a near-instant decision and we really dived in head first without looking.  We rallied behind a vision to usher in a new era of transportation for a country that has grown accustomed to a reality that was due for replacement more than 50 years ago.  This was along with all of the pollution, discomfort and hidden costs (externalities, in economist speak) that comes with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/launch_day.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Launch day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our first launch, people were delighted.  This was new, exciting and it improved quality of life in several ways beyond the quiet &amp;amp; ‘smokelessness’ of the vehicles themselves.  We were hitting our target numbers and people were feeling pretty optimistic about where we might go next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the experience of many early-stage entrepreneurs, I cannot think of a single time that somebody told me that what we are trying to accomplish is impossible.  As foreigners operating in a developing economy, it tends to sound more like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you can’t make it work, there’s no hope for the rest of us&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I reflect on my life so far, my circumstances have been extrememly fortunate.  I have many talents and have always had plenty of access to opportunity.  The system works well for me.  So I work hard and generally I get good results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/gilbert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the modern era likes to promote itself as a champion of equal opportunity, Filipinos have become well-adjusted to a life lived on the margin of that system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankie’s roots were also much closer to the margin.  As much as he wanted to keep up with his friends (myself included) in their adventures, the cruel realities of his roots would show themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here I am again, in the middle to two worlds, to the left is the world that is keen to reward talent and usher in the future as fast as possible. To the right is a world full of people working hard just to keep their head above water and searching frantically for a lifeline.  As the waters rise, the number of frantic swimmers will be only increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/maria.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Maria&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through knowing our history that we have the best chance of ensuring that this transition we are undertaking will produce a truly better future. I won’t pretend that I know the solution but I am as committed as ever to keep fighting to make this solution work, whatever it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Piccard is dreaming that humanity will rise to a new level, will trust the winds (and the weathermen) to take us out of the challenges of today.  It is people like him that help me to keep my eyes on the horizon.  To watch for the silver lining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedal-power/sunset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="solar-impulse" /><summary type="html">In a salute to the 1000 solution milestone of the Solar Impulse Foundation, This story is a bit of an hommage to the immensely inspiring 2010 TED talk by Captain Bertrand Piccard titled ‘My Solar-Powered Adventure’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SE Asia’s Labelled Solutions for water cleanup.</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/se-asias-water-cleanup-solutions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SE Asia’s Labelled Solutions for water cleanup." /><published>2021-04-12T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/se-asias-water-cleanup-solutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/se-asias-water-cleanup-solutions/">&lt;p&gt;Here we are, one thousand solutions closer to a cleaner planet.  With the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/beyond-1000-solutions&quot;&gt;#beyond1000solutions&lt;/a&gt; campaign, Solar Impulse is gearing up to bring the forward the next wave of Cleantech into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the ball rolling for the next phase, I’ve put together a short list of some of the solutions getting developed across SE Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-broad-categories&quot;&gt;The broad categories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, SE Asia sits at 16 labelled solutions.  I’ve broken them down into 3 broad themes (I guess that makes me a lumper, not a splitter):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Category&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Labelled Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cleaning up our water&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Getting more efficient&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Better, Cleaner Mobility&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For sure, some will contest my very crude categorizations.  I’d encourage them to also write an article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;by-country&quot;&gt;By country&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By country, it’s probably no surprise to anyone that Singapore leads the pack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Labelled Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Singapore&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Philippines&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;South Korea&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Taiwan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thailand&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the obvious bias that would come along with me trying to pick favourites within a group that our company is active in, I’m only going to talk about my picks from Category 1 &amp;amp; 2.  This article is going to be about water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would consider myself as a capable student of pollution solutions in general.  However, I claim no expertise or specialized knowledge in any of the technologies mentioned below.  I have not reviewed any information beyond what has been made publicy available on Solar Impulse and their own webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cleaning-up-our-water&quot;&gt;Cleaning up our water&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no question that global water resources are deteriorating.  This decline comes from various factors including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct chemical pollution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;micro-plastics overtaking fish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fertilizer and erosion runoff killing the world’s coastal ecosystems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We desperately need to improve our track record on hydro-externalities.  The 3 solutions below each endeavour to accomplish that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-ecoworth&quot;&gt;1. &lt;a href=&quot;http://ecoworth-tech.com/&quot;&gt;EcoWorth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;solar-impulse-page&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/efficient-solutions/carbon-fibre-aerogel-cfa&quot;&gt;Solar Impulse Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EcoWorth is targeting organics in wastewater.  Organics are a broad category which include most of the contaminants causing bad smells in most of the region’s urban lakes and waterways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this technology, however, the ‘valuable organics’ that they are targeting appear to be some fom of spilled oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find the video a little hard to understand, but take note of the oily, yellow film on top of the water.  Absorbent pillows like these are often used in oil spills on the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0_ctmxYjVgI&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the many pipelines and other oil-producing facilities across the world, these kinds of absorbent materials definitely have widespread demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term for a material that strongly repels water is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Cat’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  Just kidding, it’s considered a ‘hydrophobic’ material and there are some great video demonstrations like this one out there in the cloud&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ls_ISb7lG-I&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-electro-contaminant-removal-system&quot;&gt;2. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tridentwater.com.sg/&quot;&gt;Electro-contaminant removal system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;solar-impulse-page-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/efficient-solutions/electro-contaminant-removal-ecr-system&quot;&gt;Solar Impulse Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ECR targets contaminated wastewater by applying electric fields which cause dissolved contaminants to lump together or coagulate (like your blood, when you get cut).  Today, this process is often done using chemicals called floculants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yFlrfZK8ErU&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding chemical usage with this approach, is certainly attractive and I look forward to seeing more.
They are targetting phosphorus, even 10 years ago, concerns were being raised about phosphorus shortages in the coming decades.  Now that phosphorus has become a popular battery material, recovering the material from wastewater should be a high priority going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-plakman&quot;&gt;3. PlakMan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;solar-impulse-page-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/efficient-solutions/plakman&quot;&gt;Solar Impulse Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ocean Plastics is a sector where the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/figure/waste-hierarchy-8-Eventually-the-higher-concepts-of-waste-management-such-as-3R-and_fig1_303369997&quot;&gt;Cleaner Production Pyramid&lt;/a&gt; plays a hugely important role.  The shear volume of plastics entering oceans every day is difficult to fathom.  To really make a dent on this issue will require solutions at every level of the pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/19x7ur_vCv0&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that collection/recovery, sits so low on the pyramid, they will probably be categorized as among the most expensive solutions. But that doesn’t mean it’s not necessary.  When PlakMan’s boats hit the water to start sucking up plastic, I hope careful thought will be  given to the location of their initial deployments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said, I’m very happy to see new groups coming in to join the effort.  Humanity has had quite the party since first discovering plastics.  The cleanup job is substantial and many hands make lighter work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;wrap-up&quot;&gt;Wrap up&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, some of my thoughts above have been helpful in looking at where we might go with these solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since you’re here, feel free to look around and learn more about our own solution.  You can check out our &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/efficient-solutions/sune&quot;&gt;Solar Impulse profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very excited to see these projects continue to build steam as we move &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarimpulse.com/beyond-1000-solutions&quot;&gt;#beyond1000solutions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="solar-impulse" /><summary type="html">Here we are, one thousand solutions closer to a cleaner planet. With the #beyond1000solutions campaign, Solar Impulse is gearing up to bring the forward the next wave of Cleantech into the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My First Lung Fractal</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/fractals/lungs/dr-geo/first-lung-fractal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Lung Fractal" /><published>2021-01-14T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/fractals/lungs/dr-geo/first-lung-fractal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/fractals/lungs/dr-geo/first-lung-fractal/">&lt;p&gt;Since I first moved to the Philippines, the air pollution has been one of the hardest features to come to grips with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seem to have especially sensitive lungs as I come down with lung infections 2 to 3 times a year and it lingers for several weeks meanwhile nobody around me ever seems to get sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about that, the coronavirus has given people all sorts of reasons to pay more attention to their lungs in 2020 and 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a thing for fractals and lungs are one of the famous examples of fractals that make an impact on our everyday life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atsjournals.org/doi/full/10.1164/rccm.200308-1107OC&quot;&gt;One study estimated a whopping 480 million alveoli&lt;/a&gt; in the lungs of an average adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a diametre of 0.2mm across, you need 8 of them to provide 1mm^2 of oxygen:blood interface.  This gives me a total surface are of 60m^2.  While &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reference.com/science/surface-area-human-lungs-ffc6ae1756c2f2e&quot;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/bitesize/guides/zwyfxfr/revision/4&quot;&gt;internet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulmonary_alveolus&quot;&gt;sources&lt;/a&gt; yield 50 to 100 m^2; about the size of a tennis court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To hit those kinds of numbers from a structure that bifurcates (branches or splits into 2), you need 29 levels of branching.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1474667016387791&quot;&gt;Meanwhile, this study models branching down to 23 levels&lt;/a&gt;.  My computer starts to seriously slow down around 12.  Poor little bugger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/dr-geo/&quot;&gt;Dr Geo&lt;/a&gt;, a pretty cool open-source geometry drawing program with a Smalltalk interface.  This is totally new territory for me but I was able to get a branching fractal to make a crude approximation of a lung structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give it a shot, windows users will probably need to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://ubuntu.com/tutorials/ubuntu-on-windows#1-overview&quot;&gt;Ubuntu in Windows&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-smalltalk&quot; data-lang=&quot;smalltalk&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; figure angle alpha beta strand centre edge &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;DrGeoFigure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;angle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;freeValue:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;angle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;degreesToRadians&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;beta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;freeValue:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;360&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;angle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;degreesToRadians&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;centre&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;point:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;edge&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;point:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;strand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; p1 p2 p3  seg &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;middleOf:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;and:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;rotate:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;center:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s1&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;angle:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; 
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;rotate:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;center:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s1&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;angle:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;beta&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; 
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;seg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;segment:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;s1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;to:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;ifTrue:&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; 
			&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;seg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;large&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;ifTrue:&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; 
			&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;strand&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p1&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p2&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;strand&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p1&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p3&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;ifTrue:&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; 
			&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;segment:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;to:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; 
			&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;segment:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;to:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;p3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
		 &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;strand&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;centre&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;edge&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;value:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="fractals" /><category term="lungs" /><category term="dr-geo" /><summary type="html">Since I first moved to the Philippines, the air pollution has been one of the hardest features to come to grips with.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Supercapacitors for LSEVs</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/supercapacitors/supercapacitors-for-lsevs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supercapacitors for LSEVs" /><published>2021-01-09T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2021-01-09T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/supercapacitors/supercapacitors-for-lsevs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/supercapacitors/supercapacitors-for-lsevs/">&lt;p&gt;Supercapacitors increase battery efficiency by protecting the battery and other system components from excessive stress, and they enable onboard energy capture to reduce the energy cost for vehicle operation. Combining supercapacitors, batteries and onboard energy harvesting improves overall system operation efficiency and allows the vehicle to travel further on a single charge, compared to the battery alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lois Gray</name></author><category term="supercapacitors" /><summary type="html">Supercapacitors increase battery efficiency by protecting the battery and other system components from excessive stress, and they enable onboard energy capture to reduce the energy cost for vehicle operation. Combining supercapacitors, batteries and onboard energy harvesting improves overall system operation efficiency and allows the vehicle to travel further on a single charge, compared to the battery alone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The role of technology in bringing us to a Carbon-neutral Future - Presentation for CUNY’s Administration of Global Institutions class</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/presentations/carbon-neutral/cuny-global-institutions-presentation-he-role-of-technology-in-bringing-us-to-a-carbon-neutral-future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The role of technology in bringing us to a Carbon-neutral Future - Presentation for CUNY’s Administration of Global Institutions class" /><published>2020-04-18T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2020-04-18T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/presentations/carbon-neutral/cuny-global-institutions-presentation--he-role-of-technology-in-bringing-us-to-a-carbon-neutral-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/presentations/carbon-neutral/cuny-global-institutions-presentation-he-role-of-technology-in-bringing-us-to-a-carbon-neutral-future/">&lt;p&gt;As the new school year came along, I got the chance to come in for another of Professor Binda’s classes on Administration of Global Institutions at the City University of New York (CUNY).  Once again they were discussing the ASEAN zone but our exciting news this time was getting accepted as SE Asia’s first labelled solution of the Solar Impulse Foundation.  Very exciting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/sunE-cuny-presentation-apr-2020.pdf&quot;&gt;Please click here to access: The role of technology in bringing us to a Carbon-neutral Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that some of them will be able to approach their future posts equipped with some insights about the positive possibilities that a carbon market can create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="carbon-neutral" /><summary type="html">As the new school year came along, I got the chance to come in for another of Professor Binda’s classes on Administration of Global Institutions at the City University of New York (CUNY). Once again they were discussing the ASEAN zone but our exciting news this time was getting accepted as SE Asia’s first labelled solution of the Solar Impulse Foundation. Very exciting Please click here to access: The role of technology in bringing us to a Carbon-neutral Future</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sunE is now a Solar Impulse Efficient Solution</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/sune-is-now-a-solar-impulse-label/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sunE is now a Solar Impulse Efficient Solution" /><published>2019-07-11T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2019-07-11T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/sune-is-now-a-solar-impulse-label</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/solar-impulse/sune-is-now-a-solar-impulse-label/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SIF_LABEL.png&quot; alt=&quot;Solar Impulse label&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sunE has been named by the Solar Impulse World Alliance as one of their 1000 efficient solutions. As part of the Solar Impulse World Alliance of Efficient Solutions, sunE will showcase our solution to innovators, investors and decision makers around the world. The official announcement will happen by solar impulse in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solar Impulse organization is spearheaded by renowned Swiss explorer Betrand Piccard who flew around the world in a solar-powered plane without using a single drop of fossil fuel. He set out on that mission to prove that today’s clean technologies can compete with conventional fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/piccard-with-solar-impulse.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Capt Bertrand Piccard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piccard is bringing together 1000 of the world’s most promising clean technology innovations and connect them to investors, and leaders from around the globe. The Solar Impulse purpose is to bridge the gap between those building the solutions and the decision makers who will implement them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sunE solution was assessed by a panel of international experts for its technological feasibility, environmental, socio-economic benefits, and economic profitability. We are proud to announce that we scored top marks in all 3 categories!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being selected as a Solar Impulse Solution is a great honour for sunE and a significant step onto the public stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sunE-w-solar-impulse-label.png&quot; alt=&quot;sunE Labelled Solution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Phil Gray</name></author><category term="solar-impulse" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tales from Trying to Improve Transportation in the Philippines - Presentation for CUNY’s Administration of Global Institutions class</title><link href="https://sunetrike.com/presentations/tranportation/cuny-global-institutions-presentation-tales-of-trying-to-improve-transportation-in-the-philippines/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tales from Trying to Improve Transportation in the Philippines - Presentation for CUNY’s Administration of Global Institutions class" /><published>2018-11-03T01:08:07+08:00</published><updated>2018-11-03T01:08:07+08:00</updated><id>https://sunetrike.com/presentations/tranportation/cuny-global-institutions-presentation-tales-of-trying-to-improve-transportation-in-the-philippines</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sunetrike.com/presentations/tranportation/cuny-global-institutions-presentation-tales-of-trying-to-improve-transportation-in-the-philippines/">&lt;p&gt;As a follow-on to our participation in the 2018 Smart Infrastructure Challenge, I got the very cool opportunity to share some of my experiences with Professor Binda’s class on Administration of Global Institutions at the City University of New York (CUNY).  They were reviewing the ASEAN zone and so I talked a bit about my experiences with entrepreneurship in SE Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/sunE-cuny-presentation-nov-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;Please click here to access: Tales from Trying to Improve Transportation in the Philippines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the focus of the class, it was a good opportunity to summarize &amp;amp; synthesize some of the research I’d done on Public-Private Partnerships (P3) during the Smart Infrastructure Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;newsletter_wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;Interested in hearing more from us? &lt;a href=&quot;/newsletter/&quot;&gt; Check out our newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Allan Gray</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="tranportation" /><summary type="html">As a follow-on to our participation in the 2018 Smart Infrastructure Challenge, I got the very cool opportunity to share some of my experiences with Professor Binda’s class on Administration of Global Institutions at the City University of New York (CUNY). They were reviewing the ASEAN zone and so I talked a bit about my experiences with entrepreneurship in SE Asia. Please click here to access: Tales from Trying to Improve Transportation in the Philippines</summary></entry></feed>